<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on </title>
    <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Robert Kubinec</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.robertkubinec.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Proposed Model for Partial Identification of SARS-CoV2 Infection Rates Given Observed Tests and Cases</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/post/kubinec_model_draft/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/post/kubinec_model_draft/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In recent days as more and more data is available on observed case counts of the SARS-CoV2 coronavirus there are also increasing attempts to infer infection rates from these case counts. Furthermore, policy makers like Deborah Bix have begun to question whether the predictions of epidemiological models are far worse than the observed data.1 By contrast, in this paper I show that it is impossible to infer the true number of infected people from observed tests and cases alone, although it is possible to infer the effect of suppression policies on the relative rates of infectious growth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating Conjoint Survey Experiments</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/post/conjoint_power_simulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/post/conjoint_power_simulation/</guid>
      <description>Background Conjoint survey experiments have become more popular in political science since the publication of Hainmueller, Hopkins and Yamamoto (2014). However, analysis of the statistical of power of conjoint experiments is difficult using standard parametric techniques because of the use of multiple treatments, interaction effects and paired vignettes. To that end, I have conducted the following simulation experiment to demonstrate the statistical properties of the conjoint experiment for my online survey experiment “Politically-Connected Firms and the Military-Clientelist Complex in North Africa” (see SocArchiv Draft).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>idealstan: an R Package for Ideal Point Modeling with Stan</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/post/stancon2018_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/post/stancon2018_paper/</guid>
      <description>This is a paper that was presented at the StanCon2018 conference on Bayesian inference with the Stan Hamiltonian Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) method. Video of my talk is available here.
Introduction This notebook introduces idealstan, a new R package front-end to Stan that allows for flexible modeling of a class of latent variable models known as ideal point models. Ideal point modeling is a form of dimension reduction, and shares similarities with multi-dimensional scaling, factor analysis and item-response theory.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>