<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Methodology on </title>
    <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/tags/methodology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Methodology on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Robert Kubinec</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.robertkubinec.com/tags/methodology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>When Groups Fall Apart: Measuring Transnational Polarization with Twitter from the Arab Uprisings</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/islam-sec/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/islam-sec/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Scholars continue to disagree as to what extent international social connections act as a conduit to influence contentious politics within states. To answer this question, we provide the first rigorous and real-time measure of transnational ideological diffusion across sectarian groups by employing a novel statistical method and new data to capture the transnational dynamics of polarization after the Arab Uprisings of 2011. As authoritarian governments fell, populations in several states polarized between secularists and Islamists over what kind of regime was to replace the ousted one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Two-Way Fixed Effects Model Is Difficult to Interpret, and What to Do About It</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/fixed-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/fixed-effects/</guid>
      <description>Abstract The two-way fixed effects (FE) model, an increasingly popular method for modeling time-series cross-section (TSCS) data, is substantively difficult to interpret because the model&amp;rsquo;s estimates are a complex amalgamation of variation in the over-time and cross-sectional effects. We demonstrate this complexity in the two-way FE estimate through mathematical exposition. As an illustration, we develop a novel simulation that enables us to generate TSCS data with varying over-time and cross-sectional effects and examine the behavior of the two-way FE model as these effects change.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>