<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Methodology on </title>
    <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/tags/methodology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Methodology on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Robert Kubinec</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/methodology/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Variation in the Cross-Section and Over Time: Harnessing Fixed Effects</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/fixed-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/fixed-effects/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we compare when we run a fixed effects (FE) model on time-series cross-sectional data? If we place
the FEs on the cases, then the coefficients compare one time point to another for the same case. If we place
the FEs on the time points, then the coefficients compare one case to another at the same point in time. If we
place the FEs on both the cases and time points in the same model — two-way FEs — then this model removes
confounders that are fixed over time or across cases, but at a cost: the coefficients combine cross-sectional and
temporal variance in a way that does not clearly describe how cases differ from one another or how these cases
change over time. We urge researchers to avoid employing two-way FEs and instead to focus on choosing a
model that directly speaks to the research question of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Islamist-Secularist Polarization during the Arab Uprisings</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/islam-sec/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/islam-sec/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholars continue to disagree as to how far contentious politics diffuses within and across states and by what mechanisms it does so. We use new data and empirical measures to test polarization during and after the Arab Uprisings of 2010-12. After authoritarian governments began to fall, populations in several states began to polarize between secularists and Islamists over what kind of regime was to replace the ousted one. We hypothesize that this Islamist-secularist polarization was triggered by catalytic events (such as Muslim Brotherhood electoral victory in Egypt) and diffused transnationally owing to social media and satellite television, dividing anti-status-quo actors throughout the region. To examine polarization over time, we collect a comprehensive dataset on elite and citizen Twitter accounts across Arab countries after the Arab Spring. Using item-response models, we model polarization as the difference in latent ideological position between elites, and we show how polarization within countries changes over time in response to exogenous political shocks. By doing so we are the first to offer compelling statistical evidence of the endogenous process of polarization across competing ideological groups and states.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
