<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on </title>
    <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Robert Kubinec</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Absence Makes the Ideal Points Sharper: An Ordinal IRT Model for Complete-Data Rollcall Vote Modeling</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/bayesian-irt/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/bayesian-irt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I put forward a Bayesian IRT model that can handle legislators absences as a separate category of data for determining legislator ideal points. The estimation uses the concept of a hurdle model to deflate the probabilities of legislator&amp;rsquo;s votes by the probability of absences. The model produces a single set of ideal points, but utilizes different parameters for bill absence points. Compared to DW-Nominate, this model tends to produce more moderate estimates of US Congresspeople&amp;rsquo;s ideal points because it can model roll-call votes where there are very few opposing votes. For parliamentary data, the model provides much more precise estimates, especially in legislatures with very high rates of absence. Additionally, the model can incorporate absentions as a middle category between yes and no votes for legislatures with high rates of abstentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An R package providing this model, along with other standard IRT ideal point models, is under development. Current source code is available via &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/saudiwin/idealstan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;. The estimation is done via MCMC with the Stan modeling language.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Business Influence on Democratization</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/dissertation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/dissertation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my dissertation, I theorize that pro-authoritarian coalitions are more successful at undermining transitional democracies when elites who make up the coalition are strongly unified around the goal of regime change as opposed to lesser political aims. In Tunisia, where I undertook field research for eight months, I found that there are plenty of elites who pine for a return to the days of the dictator Ben Ali, and that these elites even went so far as to form a political party, Nidaa Tounes, that obtained the greatest numbers of seats in Tunisia&amp;rsquo;s parliament in 2014. However, this party has failed in many of its anti-democratic aims, such as passing legislation granting amnesty to corrupt businessmen from the prior regime. By contrast, in Egypt, a pro-authoritarian coalition led by the military has brought about a stable and increasingly repressive dictatorship that has stamped out all dissent. I argue that in Egypt, the economic influence of the military helped keep potential rivals, namely powerful businesspeople, strictly in-line with the military-led coalition, securing a stable transition to dictatorship. Tunisia, by contrast, lacks such an actor capable of preventing elites from squabbling with each other and undermining the success of the pro-authoritarian Nidaa Tounes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, I am testing hypotheses derived about business participation in elections from my field research through an online survey being fielded in Egypt, Algeria and Tunisia. The survey looks at whether firms that are more connected to the military and that depend on the government for various kinds of favors are also more likely to be involved in funding political parties. The survey uses Facebook as a targeting device to ensure that businesspeople are recruited into the online panel.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
