<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on </title>
    <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Robert Kubinec</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Variation in the Cross-Section and Over Time: Harnessing Fixed Effects</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/fixed-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/fixed-effects/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we compare when we run a fixed effects (FE) model on time-series cross-sectional data? If we place
the FEs on the cases, then the coefficients compare one time point to another for the same case. If we place
the FEs on the time points, then the coefficients compare one case to another at the same point in time. If we
place the FEs on both the cases and time points in the same model — two-way FEs — then this model removes
confounders that are fixed over time or across cases, but at a cost: the coefficients combine cross-sectional and
temporal variance in a way that does not clearly describe how cases differ from one another or how these cases
change over time. We urge researchers to avoid employing two-way FEs and instead to focus on choosing a
model that directly speaks to the research question of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link to paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://virginia.box.com/shared/static/n8cdbwylfldn426gyalc8nfpc9lxf4vl.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Business Influence on Democratization</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/dissertation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/dissertation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my dissertation, I theorize that pro-authoritarian coalitions are more successful at undermining transitional democracies when elites who make up the coalition are strongly unified around the goal of regime change as opposed to lesser political aims. In Tunisia, where I undertook field research for eight months, I found that there are plenty of elites who pine for a return to the days of the dictator Ben Ali, and that these elites even went so far as to form a political party, Nidaa Tounes, that obtained the greatest numbers of seats in Tunisia&amp;rsquo;s parliament in 2014. However, this party has failed in many of its anti-democratic aims, such as passing legislation granting amnesty to corrupt businessmen from the prior regime. By contrast, in Egypt, a pro-authoritarian coalition led by the military has brought about a stable and increasingly repressive dictatorship that has stamped out all dissent. I argue that in Egypt, the economic influence of the military helped keep potential rivals, namely powerful businesspeople, strictly in-line with the military-led coalition, securing a stable transition to dictatorship. Tunisia, by contrast, lacks such an actor capable of preventing elites from squabbling with each other and undermining the success of the pro-authoritarian Nidaa Tounes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on my field research, I implemented an online survey targeted at businesspeople in Tunisia, Algeria and Egypt with a sample of nearly 2,500 business managers and employees. I use an embedded experiment to see how party appeals to businesses, such as for protection from expropriation or for perks from government licenses and contracts, stimulate businesspeople to offer support to parties, such as electoral funding or instructing their employees to vote for a candidate. I find that firm&amp;rsquo;s incentives to engage politically vary on the firm&amp;rsquo;s market position, size and relationship vis-a-vis government agencies, but that political-economic institutions, especially the Egyptian military, have a pronounced effect on increasing business political engagement in the aggregate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My work sheds light on the processes through which powerful elite coalitions are built during the chaotic periods of revolutions and democratic transitions. By so doing, I advance the field by pinpointing the conditions under which anti-democratic coalitions are successful, and when they are likely to fail and let democracy survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link to online survey paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://virginia.box.com/shared/static/xq018i5613wgwwbeh4j7bongkrtluvsg.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and appendix &lt;a href=&#34;https://virginia.box.com/shared/static/715c8h7nwdvgpqszhknl6xq46xr2slhe.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Islamist-Secularist Polarization during the Arab Uprisings</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/islam-sec/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/islam-sec/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholars continue to disagree as to how far contentious politics diffuses within and across states and by what mechanisms it does so. We use new data and empirical measures to test polarization during and after the Arab Uprisings of 2010-12. After authoritarian governments began to fall, populations in several states began to polarize between secularists and Islamists over what kind of regime was to replace the ousted one. We hypothesize that this Islamist-secularist polarization was triggered by catalytic events (such as Muslim Brotherhood electoral victory in Egypt) and diffused transnationally owing to social media and satellite television, dividing anti-status-quo actors throughout the region. To examine polarization over time, we collect a comprehensive dataset on elite and citizen Twitter accounts across Arab countries after the Arab Spring. Using item-response models, we model polarization as the difference in latent ideological position between elites, and we show how polarization within countries changes over time in response to exogenous political shocks. By doing so we are the first to offer compelling statistical evidence of the endogenous process of polarization across competing ideological groups and states.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Absence Makes the Ideal Points Sharper: An Ordinal IRT Model for Complete-Data Rollcall Vote Modeling</title>
      <link>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/bayesian-irt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.robertkubinec.com/project/bayesian-irt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Estimating legislator ideal points from roll-call voting data has become a powerful tool for understanding legislative behavior and polarization within legislatures over time. However, the dominant approaches in the field tend to ignore both absences and abstentions in roll-call votes even though it is very likely that absences and abstentions represent a form of strategic behavior. In emerging democracies like Tunisia, this lacuna is particularly problematic because legislator absence may occur very frequently, and resulting estimates that exclude absences are either very imprecise or significantly biased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a remedy for this situation, I put forward a Bayesian IRT model that can handle legislators absences as a separate category of data for determining legislator ideal points. The estimation uses the concept of a hurdle model to deflate the probabilities of legislator&amp;rsquo;s votes by the probability of absences. The model produces a single set of ideal points, but utilizes different parameters for bill absence points. Compared to DW-NOMINATE, this model tends to produce more moderate estimates of US Congresspeople&amp;rsquo;s ideal points because it can model roll-call votes where there are very few opposing votes. For parliamentary data, the model provides much more precise estimates, especially in legislatures with very high rates of absence. Additionally, the model can incorporate absentions as a middle category between yes and no votes for legislatures with high rates of abstentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An R package providing this model, along with other standard IRT ideal point models, is under development. Current source code is available from my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/saudiwin/idealstan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Github page&lt;/a&gt;. The estimation is done via MCMC within the Stan modeling language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Link to paper &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/saudiwin/idealstan/blob/develop/Kubinec%20-%20Absence%20Makes%20the%20Ideal%20Points%20Sharper.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
